Guide to the Advertising Ephemera Collection, 1850s-1980s
Advertising Ephemera collection 1850s-1980s
Advertising Ephemera. Duke University. David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
35 Linear Feet 9650 Items
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. There may be a 48-hour delay in obtaining these materials.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
Items were purchased by or transferred to the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library in the 1970s and the 1990s.
Collection Overview
The Advertising Ephemera Collection is composed of single advertisements, product and trade catalogs, advertising pamphlets, and broadsides. The advertisements are primarily American and from the late 19th and early to mid 20th century. The collection is divided into broad subject categories, based on the primary type of product or service being advertised, which are arranged in alphabetical order. Within each subject category material is divided based upon the form of the material; leaflets, letters, and sheets printed on both sides; trade cards (mechanical, metamorphic, see-thru, shape, fabric inserts, unusual feature, postcards and insert cards); booklets; special categories; and miscellaneous. A subseries of foreign advertising material consists predominately of travel related literature and is arrange alphabetically by country. The arrangement of oversize materials parallels the original arrangement.
The researcher should note that trade catalogs that are pamphlets may be found in several places in the Perkins Library: this collections; individually in the stacks as fully cataloged items; or as part of groups of old pamphlets for which the cataloging was by main entry only. Advertising broadsides may also be found in the Broadsides Collection and many collections of manuscripts also contain advertising materials.
Some useful reference sources for gathering further information on this type of material include:
Romaine, Lawrence B., "A Guide to American Trade Catalogs," 1944-1900 (New York, 1960).
Hammond, Dorothy, "Advertising Collectibles of Times Past," (Des Moines, Iowa, 1974).
Kaduck, John M., "Advertising Trade Cards," (Des Moines, Iowa, 1976).
McQuarry, Jim, "Collectors Guide to Advertising Cards," (Gas City, Indiana, 1975).
Additions to the collection have not been processed and therefore to do reflect the arrangement of the rest of the collection. Please refer to the detailed description below for more information about their content.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Advertising
Advertising, American
Advertising cards
Advertising -- Tourist trade
Broadsides
Trade catalogues
Furniture -- Catalogs
Cookery
Clothing and dress
Household appliances
Recipes
Health products
House furnishings industry and trade
Automobiles -- Catalogs
Building materials -- Catalogs
Patent medicines -- Catalogs
Machinery -- Catalogs
Equipment and Supplies -- Catalogs
Catalogs, Commercial
Playbills
Pamphlets
Ephemera
Cookbooks
Business cards
Memorabilia
John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History
Contents of Collection
- Advertising Ephemera Subject Files
  - Advertising Business, (1 folder) (Box 1)
    Additional oversize materials in Box 63.
  - Airplanes, Astrology, Magic & Dreams, (1 folder)
  - Attorneys, (1 folder)
  - Automobiles and Roads, (4 folders)
  - Badges, Stickers, and Stamps, (1 folder)
  - Banks & Finance, (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - Beauty Parlors & Barber Shops, (1 folder)
  - Bicycles, (1 folder)
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, (3 folders)
    Publisher and bookseller catalogs. Some magzine and subscription advertisements.
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, (5 folders) (Box 3)
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing, (4 folders) (Box 4)
  - Boots and Shoes, (2 folders)
  - Building Supplies, (6 folders) (Box 5)
    Building supplies, equipment, and services. Architectural ornaments and building matertials.
  - Building Supplies, (5 folders) (Box 6)
  - Burial, (1 folder) (Box 7)
  - Carriages, Buggies, and Horse Paraphernalia, (3 folders)
  - Clothing, (5 folders) (Box 8)
  - Commercial and Trade Organizations, (1 folder) (Box 9)
  - Computers, (1 folder)
  - Dance, (1 folder)
  - Drama, (3 folders)
    Chiefly playbills for theater performances in Philadelphia and New York.
  - Drama, (5 folders) (Box 10)
  - Drama, (5 folders) (Box 11)
  - Drama, (4 folders) (Box 12)
  - Education, (3 folders) (Box 13)
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals, (1 folder)
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals, (4 folders) (Box 14)
  - Eyeglasses, (1 folder)
  - Farm Machinery and Implements, (5 folders) (Box 15)
  - Farm Machinery and Implements, (3 folders) (Box 16)
  - Fertilizers, (3 folders)
  - Food, (3 folders) (Box 17)
  - Foreign Countries
    Catalogs and brochures for foreign travel and package tours. Includes museum and retaurant guides, shopping guides, and regional maps.
    - Albania, (1 folder)
    - Austria, (1 folder)
    - Belgium, (2 folders)
    - Brazil, (1 folder)
    - Canada, (1 folder)
    - China, (1 folder)
    - Cuba, (1 folder)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 18)
    - England, (5 folders)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 19)
    - England, (2 folders)
    - France, (3 folders)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 20)
    - Germany, (1 folder)
    - Greece, (1 folder)
    - Hungary, (1 folder)
    - Ireland, (1 folder)
    - Israel, (1 folder)
    - Italy, (2 folders)
    - Japan, (1 folder)
    - Mexico, (1 folder)
    - Monaco, (1 folder)
    - Netherlands, (1 folder)
    - Philippines, (1 folder)
    - Puerto Rico, (1 folder)
  - Foreign Countries (Box 21)
    - Romania, (1 folder)
    - Scotland, (1 folder)
    - South Africa, (1 folder)
    - Sweden, (1 folder)
    - Switzerland, (1 folder)
    - Tours-Foreign, (1 folder)
    - Turkey, (1 folder)
    - Yugoslavia, (1 folder)
  - Furniture, (5 folders) (Box 22)
    Chiefly catalogs for school, library, and office furniture. Some catalogs for home furniture. For rugs, lamps, fixtures, and other home related items see Home Furnishings. Additional oversize materials in Box 63.
  - Furniture, (5 folders) (Box 23)
  - Furniture, (4 folders) (Box 24)
  - Furniture, (4 folders) (Box 25)
  - Furs & Skins, (1 folder) (Box 26)
  - Guns, (1 folder)
  - Hair Goods, (1 folder)
  - Hardware, (4 folders)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, (4 folders) (Box 27)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, (4 folders) (Box 28)
  - Health and Patent Medicines, (4 folders) (Box 29)
  - Heating and Fuel, (1 folder) (Box 30)
  - Horticulture, (3 folders)
  - Household Appliances and Supplies, (4 folders) (Box 31)
  - Household Furnishings, (4 folders) (Box 32)
  - Household Furnishings, (2 folders) (Box 33)
  - Houses and Buildings, (1 folder)
  - Insecticides, (1 folder) (Box 34)
  - Insurance, (2 folders)
  - Jewelry, Watches, and Clocks, (2 folders)
  - Lectures, (1 folder)
  - Lighting, (2 folders) (Box 35)
  - Liquor, Wines, and Spirits, (1 folder)
  - Livestock, Poultry, Bees, etc., (2 folders)
  - Lotteries, (1 folder)
  - Lumber, Woodworking, and Related Machinery, (1 folder) (Box 36)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (3 folders)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (5 folders) (Box 37)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (3 folders) (Box 38)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (4 folders) (Box 39)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (2 folders) (Box 40)
  - Machinery and Instruments, (4 folders) (Box 41)
  - Mercantile Business, (1 folder) (Box 42)
  - Mining, (1 folder)
  - Miscellaneous, (1 folder)
  - Moving Pictures, (1 folder)
  - Music, (1 folder)
  - Music Concerts, (2 folders)
  - Musical Instruments, (1 folder) (Box 43)
  - Nuclear Power, (1 folder)
  - Office Supplies, (3 folders)
  - Paper and Paper Products, (1 folder)
  - Penmanship, (1 folder)
  - Pets, (1 folder) (Box 44)
  - Photography and Projection Equipment, (1 folder)
  - Radios, (1 folder)
  - Railroads, (3 folders)
  - Railroads, (4 folders) (Box 45)
  - Railroads, (4 folders) (Box 46)
  - Real Estate, (1 folder) (Box 47)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, (3 folders)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, (4 folders) (Box 48)
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel, (3 folders) (Box 49)
  - Rubber Goods, (1 folder)
  - Sewing Equipment and Supplies, (1 folder)
  - Sporting Goods, (2 folders) (Box 50)
  - Steamships and Boats, (2 folders)
  - Steamships and Boats, (4 folders) (Box 51)
  - Telegraphs and Telephones, (1 folder) (Box 52)
  - Textiles, (2 folders)
  - Toiletries, (1 folder)
  - Toys, (1 folder)
  - Utilities, (1 folder)
- Advertising Ephemera Subject Files - Oversize Materials
  - Automobiles and Roads (Box 53)
  - Beauty Parlors and Barbershops
  - Books, Publishing, and Printing
  - Boots and Shoes
  - Building Supplies (Box 54)
  - Building Supplies (Box 55)
  - Carriages, Buggies, and Horse Paraphernalia
  - Clothing
  - Drama (Box 56)
  - Education
  - Expositions, Fairs, & Festivals
  - Fertilizers
  - Food
    Additional Oversize materials held in Box 63.
  - Foreign Countries
    - England
    - France
    - Germany
    - Yugoslavia
  - Furniture
  - Furs and Skins (Box 57)
  - Health and Patent Medicines
  - Heating and Fuel
  - Horticulture
  - Household Appliances
  - Household Furnishings (Box 58)
  - Insurance
  - Jewelry, Watches, and Clocks
  - Lighting
  - Liquor, Wine, and Spirits
  - Livestock, Poultry, Bees, etc.
  - Lumber, Woodworking, and Related Machinery
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 59)
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 60)
  - Machinery and Instruments (Box 61)
  - Mercantile Businesses (Box 62)
  - Music
  - Musical Instruments
  - Office Supplies
  - Railroads
  - Resorts, Hotels, and Travel
  - Sewing Equipment and Supplies
  - Steamships and Boats
  - Toiletries
- Accession (2001-0034), 1860-1999
  Addition (2001-0034) (2,012 items; dated 1860-1999) contains examples of ephemera, including: House of Lights (Raleigh and Cary, N.C.) night light, Dalziel Supply Co. hanger, N. Donald Edwards Co. paper clip dispenser, FedEx golf tee, Emery Worldwide keychain, and Baird & Warner real estate jar opener.
- Accession (2002-0082), 1960s-1970s, 2 Boxes
  Addition (2002-0082) (250 items, 1.2 lin. ft.; dated 1960s-1970s) contains primarily catalogs for the flooring and carpeting retail industry, brochures, and business cards for diverse stores and services. Also includes advertising memorabilia such as rulers, sewing kits, and keychains.
- Accession (2004-0145), 1800s-1990s, 1 Box
  Addition (2004-0145) (150 items, 0.6 lin. ft.; dated [1800s]-[1990s]) contains a wide variety of promotional items, most dating from the early to mid 20th century, including cookbooks, pamphlets, brochures, direct mailings, order forms, and other items. Also includes a can opener, a contact lens case, an LP record, and two CDRs.
- Accession (2008-0311), 1850-1950, 1 Box
  Addition (2008-0311) (150 items, 0.2 lin. ft.; dated [1850]-[1950]) includes trade catalogs, booklets, brochures, and leaflets for a wide variety of industries, including books, machinery, and appliances.
- Accessions (2008-0317), (2008-0322), and (2008-0323), 1 folder (interfiled with Acc. 08/311: Box 1)
  Addition (2008-0317) (3 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1898) consists of a pamphlet advertising a Commercial Travelers' fair in New York.
  Addition (2008-0322) (3 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1913) includes a letter from Regal Tailoring to J.T. Ryan asking him to represent the company as an agent.
  Addition (2008-0323) (5 items, 0.1 lin. ft.; dated 1879) includes 5 pieces about becoming an agent for Sherman & Co.'s Centennial Illuminating Oil and Compound bar soap.